Guide to the Henry Stuart Hughes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings and Teaching Materials, 1948-1990; Series III
  - Articles and essays
    - "Is the Intellectual Obsolete?", 1956 October (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - "The Turn of the Tide", 1958 March (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - "Rassegne, Discussioni E Varieté", 1958 April (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - "How Democratic is Christian Democracy?", 1958 May (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - "Catholicism and Democracy", 1958 August (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - "Italy: The Elections and the Constituted Powers", 1958 Summer (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - "Gaullism in the Mirror of History", 1958 September (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - "A Politics of Peace", 1959 February (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - "What Should Our Foreign Policy Be?", 1959 April (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - "Mass Culture and Social Criticism", 1960 Spring (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - "The Experience of Recent History", 1961 January (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - "The Dilemmas of Modern Italian History", 1961 February (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - "The Strategy of Deterrence", 1961 March (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - "Grandeur and Misery of Guerilla Warfare", 1962 August (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - "The Cold War and the West", 1962 Winter (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - "Disengagement and NATO", 1962 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - "Against Violence and Hatred", 1963 December (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - "The Historian and the Social Scientist,", 1963 (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - "Pope John's Revolution: Secular or Religious?", 1965 December (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - "Beyond Vietnam: New Assumptions for Old", 1965 December (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - The Messianic Pose: Post-Cold War Delusions, 1966 January (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - "What's Happening to America?", 1967 Winter (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - "Crane Brinton as an Intellectual Historian", 1968 April (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - "Sanford Markham", 1969 February (Box 12, Folder 41)
    - "Emotional Disturbance and American Social Change, 1944-1969", 1969 July (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - The Need is Now to De-politicize the University, 1969 September (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Le Problème des Guerres de Liberation Nationale, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - "Vico and Contemporary Social Theory and Social History", 1969 (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - "The Second Year of the Cold War", 1970 (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - "Editor's Introduction" [to Croce, Benedetto, History of the Kingdom of Naples], 1970 (Box 12, Folder 47)
    - "The Controversy about Violence in Modern History", 1972 (Box 12, Folder 48)
    - "Social Theory in a New Context", 1980 (Box 12, Folder 49)
    - "Contemporary Historiography: Progress, Paradigms, and the Regression Towards Positivism", 1982 (Box 12, Folder 50)
    - "European Intellectual History, 1884-1984: The Socialization of Ideas", 1984 December (Box 12, Folder 51)
    - "Arnaldo Momigliano: Universal History, Hellenistic Civilization, and the Jews", 1988 (Box 12, Folder 52)
  - Books
    - An Essay for Our Times
      - Correspondence, notes and drafts, 1948-1951, undated (Box 13, Folder 53)
      - Reviews, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 54)
    - Oswald Spengler: A Critical Estimate
      - Correspondence, notes and drafts, 1950-1952, 1962-1970 (Box 13, Folder 55)
      - Reviews, 1952-1953 (Box 13, Folder 56)
    - The United States and Italy
      - Correspondence, notes and drafts, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 57)
      - Reviews, 1957, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 58)
    - Consciousness and Society
      - Correspondence, 1960-1979 (Box 13, Folder 59)
      - Notes and drafts, 1956-1958, undated (Box 13, Folder 60-61)
      - Reviews, 1959 (Box 13, Folder 62)
    - Contemporary Europe [reviews], 1961-1965 (Box 13, Folder 63)
    - Approach to Peace and Other Essays [reviews], 1962-1963 (Box 13, Folder 64)
    - History as Art and Science [reviews], 1964 (Box 13, Folder 65)
    - Obstructed Path
      - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 13, Folder 66)
      - Reviews, 1968-1971 (Box 13, Folder 67)
    - The Sea Change [reviews], 1974-1977 (Box 13, Folder 68)
    - Prisoners of Hope
      - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 69)
      - Reviews, 1983-1985 (Box 13, Folder 70)
    - Sophisticated Rebels
      - Correspondence, notes and drafts, 1985-1987 (Box 13, Folder 71)
      - Reviews, 1988-1990 (Box 13, Folder 72)
    - Gentleman Rebel: The Memoirs of H. Stuart Hughes [correspondence, research material and drafts; includes biographical material], 1961-1984, undated (Box 13, Folder 73)
  - Book reviews [by HSH], 1949-1989 (Box 14, Folder 74-78)
  - Lectures, remarks, and memoranda, 1952-1990 (Box 14, Folder 79-85)
  - Student writings
    - Amherst College, 1934-1937 (Box 15, Folder 86-87)
    - Harvard University, 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 88-89)
    - Teaching materials [notes and syllabi], 1949-1975, undated (Box 15, Folder 90-91)
- Personal Papers and Photographs, 1916-1989; Series IV
  The series is arranged alphabetically by record type and includes clippings; family correspondence; diaries and notebooks; memorabilia; military papers; and photographs.
  In addition to general coverage of Hughes and his family, clippings include one folder chronicling an incident when the Department of State refused Hughes a visa to travel abroad in 1966, due to suspicions about him being a subversive. He was cleared of the charges.
  Family correspondence comprises the most substantial portion of the series. From 1928 to 1963, he wrote a letter to his mother and/or father almost every week detailing his activities. The letters begin when he was a student at Deerfield Academy, and continue through his undergraduate years at Amherst College, his graduate years at Harvard University, his service in the United States Armed Forces in Italy and France during and after the second world war, and his professorial appointments at Harvard and Stanford University. The World War II letters give detailed accounts and impressions of the war effort. Other family correspondents include his grandfathers, Charles Evans Hughes and Henry C. Stuart, his brother Charles Evans Hughes III, his sister Helen, his first wife Suzanne, and his children, Sandra and Kenneth. Files regarding the estate of Hughes' mother, Margory Stuart Hughes, and the Charles Evans Hughes Foundation, are listed under each of these correspondents.
  Diaries and notebooks include travel journals from trips made to Europe in 1935 and 1941, along with a "history notebook" which Hughes compiled during his childhood years.
  The military records contain documentation of Hughes' service in the armed forces, including allegations of subversion, of which he was later cleared. Files listed under "Department of State" and "Office of Strategic Services" comprise reports and other papers he wrote while serving in these two branches during the war.
  One folder of photographs holds small portraits of Hughes from several different periods of his life.
  - Clippings
    - General, 1961-1988 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Family, 1916, 1950, 1982, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - State Department incident, 1966, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Family correspondence
    - General, 1936-1957 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
    - Gossett, Elizabeth Hughes [sister], 1964-1981 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Hughes, Charles Evans [grandfather], 1941-1945 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Charles Evans Hughes Memorial Foundation, 1985-1989 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Hughes, Charles Evans III [brother]
      - To HSH, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - To Hughes, Margory, 1931-1933 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Hughes, Helen [sister], undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Hughes, Marjory and Charles Evans, Jr. [mother and father], 1928-1935 (Box 16, Folder 12-18)
    - Hughes, Marjory and Charles Evans, Jr. [mother and father], 1935-1946 (Box 17, Folder 19-32)
    - Hughes, Marjory and Charles Evans, Jr. [mother and father], 1946-1956 (Box 18, Folder 33-42)
    - Hughes, Marjory [mother], 1956-1963 (Box 19, Folder 43-52)
    - Marjory Hughes estate, 1965-1966 (Box 19, Folder 53)
    - Hughes, Sandra and Kenneth [children], undated (Box 19, Folder 54)
    - Hughes, Suzanne [first wife]
      - To HSH, 1958, undated (Box 19, Folder 55)
      - To Hughes, Marjory, 1953-1954, undated (Box 19, Folder 56)
    - "Joan", 1962-1963 (Box 19, Folder 57)
    - Stuart, Henry C. [grandfather]
      - General, 1937 (Box 20, Folder 58-59)
      - Clippings and memorabilia, 1920-1937 (Box 20, Folder 60)
  - Diaries and notebooks, 1935, 1943, undated (Box 20, Folder 61)
  - Memorabilia
    - Amherst College, 1934-1937, 1967-1975 (Box 20, Folder 62-63)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916-1941, undated (Box 20, Folder 64)
  - Military papers
    - Army discharge [includes allegations and response re: HSH as a subversive], 1952-1953 (Box 20, Folder 65)
    - Department of State, 1946-1947 (Box 20, Folder 66)
    - Office of Strategic Services, 1944-1945 (Box 20, Folder 67)
    - Service record, 1938-1958 (Box 20, Folder 68)
  - Photographs of HSH, 1941, 1949, undated (Box 20, Folder 69)
- Additional material, Accession 2000-M-086; 2.25
  Arranged alphabetically, the accession includes correspondence, writings, topical files, teaching materials, and audio recordings that primarily document the final decade of the life of H. Stuart Hughes. The correspondence primarily consists of letters written to Hughes from friends, colleagues, and other scholars, many of whom are also represented in Series I of the main accession. Topics range widely in a number of intellectual, personal, and professional areas.
  The accession also includes articles, reviews, speeches and talks, all filed under the heading Writings. Most of the articles and reviews are published and cover scholarly topics. Speeches and talks are separated into two categories, Notes, which give only outlines, and Texts, which provide the full content of the speech. The notes for Hughes' Senate campaign speeches provide documentation of his platform and positions and supplement other campaign materials found in the main accession. A short publication of essays looking back upon the Hughes campaign after 25 years is also filed with the Writings. A complete listing of Hughes' publications can be found in the curriculum vita folder.
  The remainder of the accession consists of teaching materials, personal papers, and ephemera. Audio tapes of the symposium honoring Hughes at his 1986 retirement are filed under "Approaches to European Intellectual History." Original audio tapes may not be played. For more information on copies created for research use consult the Audio Tapes appendix. The memorial service folder contains full texts of remarks made about Hughes after his death in 1999.
  - "Approaches to European Intellectual History" [audio tapes of a symposium honoring HSH], 1986 (Box 1)
    See: Audio Tapes Appendix
  - Correspondence
    - General (A-Y), 1983-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1989-1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Burdett, Winston, 1990, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - de Carbonnel, Lise, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cowan, Fairman C., 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Edwards, Robert L., 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ferry, W. H., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Harper and Row Publishers, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Harvard University Press, 1989-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Howe, Irving, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Joll, James, 1988-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Kapstein, John J., 1994, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Robinson, Paul, 1991-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Schorske, Carl E., 1975-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Segre-Amar, Sion, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Snyder, Jon, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - University of Chicago Press, 1990-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - University Press of New England, 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Venturi, Franco, 1989, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Vivarelli, Roberto, 1991-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Curriculum vita, 1999, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Daybooks, 1942-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Graduate students, undated (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Memorial service, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Military service, 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Passports, 1948-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Symposia, 1986, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Teaching materials
    - Lectures, [1967] (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Note cards, undated (Box 4, Folder system_indicator_2fa62452e534cdc85ba3ac97e0f7d694)
  - Writings
    - Articles and reviews by HSH, 1949-2000, undated (Box 5, Folder 34 - 42)
    - "The Hughes Campaign: 25 Years Later" [essays about the 1962 senate campaign], 1987 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Reviews of HSH's books, 1959, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Speeches and talks
      - Notes
        - General, 1948-1991 (Box 5, Folder 45 - 48)
        - Campaign speeches, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Texts, 1985-1996 (Box 5, Folder 50 - 51)
- Additional material, Accession 2005-M-063; 0.25
  This addition consists of handwritten lecture notes, most likely from the late 1980s through the mid 1990s.
  - Architects and architecture, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Italian history, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Society and culture since 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)